Aki Fukai

Lead Product Designer

+49 172 431 15 00

aki@fukai.ch

www.fukai.ch

in @fukai

Summary

I'm a full-stack Lead UX/Product Designer with over 12 years experience of building products and services from zero to one and beyond. I excel at simplifying complexity in agile, collaborative, cross-silo, well-connected environments – at eye level with product leadership.

I have a Swiss passport and live with my family in Hamburg, Germany.

Languages

German: Mother tongue

English: Full professional proficiency French: Intermediate level (CEFR B1) Japanese & isiZulu: Beginner level

Education

HAW Hamburg, Department Design Communication design (with an internship at Fork Unstable Media)

Further work experience

Before 2015

Sr. Interaction Designer (contract) **SAP** Fiori App Store (DS) Jul 2015 – Oct 2015

Sr. UX Designer Scout24 Schweiz
Search & filter UX Feb 2015 – Apr 2015

Sr. Interaction Designer (contract) **natcon7** · Renewable power plant management Dec 2013 – Oct 2014

Sr. Interaction Designer (contract) **frog** for Unify: Unified collaboration enterprise app (mobile, iPad & web). Sep 2013 – Jan 2014

UX Designer & UX Researcher (freelance)
Immonet: faceted search Jan – Apr 2013

Sr. Art Director (contract) at Razorfish for **Telefónica o2** relaunch May – Sep 2011

Freelance Art Director, Interaction
Designer, Concept/IA 1998 – 2013
Agencies i.a.: Kabel New Media AG,
IconMedialab AG, Nolte & Lauth
Clients i.a.: Aquila Capital, Audi, BMW,
Netbreeze, Mercedes-Benz, Rossmann

WORK EXPERIENCE

Design Director (remote) SDGventure Jan 2022 - present

Driving and leading product design of the impact collective – from discovery over MVP to viable business, zero to one and beyond – marrying profit with purpose. Mandates: WHATEVER.WORKS (JobRad), PlasticPlan (Henkel).

Design Director (contract, remote), WHATEVER.WORKS May 2023 – Jun 2024

Product: Co-lead, designed and shipped 12+ product initiatives end-2-end.

Enabled signing dozens of companies offering time-outs. Improved quality and TTM by introducing Shape-Up (JobRad B2B SaaS venture).

People: Created and cultivated alignment with key stakeholders. Hired and

mentored a Senior Product Designer.

DS/Tools: Built and shipped a complex application design system MVP.

Introduced multi-language tooling with Lokalise.

Lead/Sr. UX/UI Designer (freelance, remote/hybrid) Jul 2022 - Apr 2023

Clients: Babymarkt UX audit · Tagesspiegel Media Relaunch ·

Mercedes-Benz.io Design System

Lead Product Designer (contract, remote), PlasticPlan Feb - Jul 2022

Product: Designed and shipped a human-centric interface on top of an AI-

powered data service that enables companies to transparently manage

complex packaging data (Henkel B2B SaaS venture).

People: Hired and coached a Mid level Product Marketing Designer.

DS: Built and shipped complex app & product mkt. design system MVPs.

Partner & Product Designer (on site/remote) Hello Meet Jan 2018 – Mar 2024

Strategy: Co-shaped and tested C2B business model.

Product: Hypothesis driven product design and development, JTBD informed user

flows and UIs, new features, continuous improvement.

Ds: Built and shipped a mobile design system (iOS, Android, web).

Senior Product Designer, product & DS (hybrid), enfore AG Jul 2018 – May 2020

Product: B2B2C · Drove, designed and shipped multiple core design initiatives

from discovery to delivery — customer centered, multi device, at POS and online. E.g. reservations, pick-up & delivery, dashboard widgets,

online presence email & business docs.

DS: Extended a enhanced a multi-device POS & ERP application design

system for a highly complex product, driven by product initiatives.

Sr. Interaction Designer (on site) collectAI part of Otto Feb 2016 – Feb 2018

Product: Designed and shipped a white label B2B2C digital self-service for dunning, collections & payment processes, as well as the merchant's

claim management portal.

Ds: Built minimal design systems for the claim management application and

the end user facing payment flows.

Lead/Sr. Interaction Designer (contract, on site), SBB Nov 2015 – Sep 2016

Product: Defined use cases and designed the UX concept, workflows, prototypes for the GIS based iPad & web app to digitise end-to-end the railway's vegetation monitoring, assessment and procurement in the field and in the accounting office.

ps: Based on the SBB CI I've created a flexible custom UI component library and ensured the implementation quality in iPadOS and in the web.